St. Luke's Church Building Committee Records
St. Luke's Church Building Committee Records
1965-1968
St. Luke's Episcopal Church (Fairport, N.Y.)
0.5 linear feet
Records collected by Committee Chairman, Thomas Nesbit. Meeting minutes, financial reports, committee correspondence, architect correspondence, construction specifications, architectural drawings and other material related to the design and construction of a proposed new Episcopal church in Fairport, N.Y.
3192480
Biographical History
St. Luke's Church (incorporated 1887) is an Episcopal parish located in Fairport, New York (near Rochester, New York).
In the early 1960s, having outgrown their Perinton church building, the parish purchased a sixteen acre tract on Ayrault Road (later known as the Brambleridge East subdivision) in Fairport, New York. Under the auspices of rector Dustin Ordway, fund raising for a new building commenced and a Building Committee was formed. According to local press announcements at the time, "the membership of St. Luke's wanted something special... something more than 'contemporary ecclesiastical'" (The Brighton-Pittsford Post, 28 Jan 1965). The search for an architect was wide-ranging, targeting leading firms in Rochester and elsewhere, with the ultimate selection going to the large, international firm Marcel Breuer and Associates.
The selection of a world-renowned architect was greeted with much fanfare and occassioned the launch of a publicity campaign, ultimately featuring the model and presentation drawings produced by the Breuer firm. The resulting design, credited to Marcel Breuer and Herbert Beckhard, reflected "Breuer's mastaba building type, a low compact structure with a flat roof and canted sides" (Hyman, Marcel Breuer, Architect. p. 226). Detailed construction specifications were issued, to facilitate the initial bid process, but ultimately the collaboration with Breuer was postponed in April of 1966 due to difficulties with funding.
In May of 1966, St. Luke's entered into a formal arrangement with the firm of Roy D. Murphy and Associates to produce a long range development plan for the property that might eventually include the original Breuer church design. In 1968, a small church structure was completed by Creative Buildings Inc., a firm with a specialization in church construction. The Breuer design was never realized.
In addition to Chairman Thomas Nesbit, other members of the Commitee included: Raymond Beach, Mrs. Avery Beer, Robert Butterfield, Mrs. Henry Martin, Ernest Swart and Romine Foster, among others. (Fairport Herald Mail, 3 Feb 1965)
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The bulk of the material in this collection relates to the Building Committee's work with Roy D. Murphy and Associates. This material includes correspondence, proposals, a detailed analysis of the program, specificiations, drawings for an "immediate construction unit" and construction records. There is a small amount of material related to Marcel Breuer and Associates, including a few pieces of correspondence, some publicity clippings related to the project and a detailed set of construction specifications. In addition, there are several folders of general Committee documents including meeting minutes, church financial reports, and correspondence.
Arrangement of the Collection
The St. Luke's Church Building Committee Records has been arranged in three series: Committe Records containing documents related to the general work of the Building Committe; Building Project I containing records related to work with the architectural firm Marcel Breuer and Associates; and Building Project II relating to work with the architectural firm Roy D. Murphy and Associates.
Related Material
See the Marcel Breuer Papers for additional material related to an intial design for St. Luke's Church.
Subject and Genre Headings
Architects; Beckhard, Herbert.; Breuer, Marcel, 1902-1981.; Nesbit, Thomas.; Ordway, Dustin.; Roy D. Murphy and Associates.; Marcel Breuer and Associates.; Creative Buildings Incorporated.; St. Luke's Episcopal Church (Fairport, N.Y.); Architectural design.; Church architecture -- United States -- Designs and Plans.; Architecture -- United States.; Architecture -- Designs and plans.; Architecture, American.; Anglican church buildings.; Architecture -- United States -- History -- 20th century.; Architectural records.; Blueprints (reprographic copies); Correspondence.; Specifications.; Architects.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Molly Nesbit, facilitated by Barry Bergdoll, 2010.
Inventory
- Committee Records
  - Committee Meeting Minutes and Reports, Nov 1966-Jan 1968 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence (misc. consultants, contractors and suppliers), Mar 1967-Feb 1968 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Financial Reports, Jan 1966-May 1967 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Land Conveyance Documents, Nov 1966-Feb 1967 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Misc. Notes (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Building Plan I. Marcel Breuer and Associates.
  - Correspondence (includes bid proposal and architect invoice), Jan 1966-Oct 1966 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Promotional Material (Marcel Breuer and Associates)
    - St. Francis de Sales Church, Architectural Record (Nov 1967) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Published Material (newspaper clippings and copies of clippings announcing project), Jan 1965-Mar 1965 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Specifications, 18 Mar 1965 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Building Plan II. Roy D. Murphy and Associates.
  - Analysis of Program and Finance, 19 May 1966 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Building Code Documents, Nov 1967-Dec 1967 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence (includes proposals and construction records), Apr 1966-Mar 1968 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Drawings
    - Immediate Construction Unit (Dwg. No. 1-A), 30 Aug 1966-16 Sep 1966 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Specifications, 12 Apr 1967 (Box 1, Folder 14)